(upbeat music)
- [Instructor] Let us now
discuss the very important notion
or concept of indifference
set or indifference curve.
An indifference set is a set of bundles
that the consumer regard as equal, okay?
So it's a set of bundles
that the consumer regards as equal.
What that means is that
inside the elements
of an indifference set are bundles
such that for the corresponding consumer,
all those bundles feel the same.
They are indifferent
with each other, okay?
For example, suppose
we have a bundle, okay?
And then we collect or identify
all other bundles that
are indifferent to x
for this particular consumer,
and that whole set will be
the indifference curve that contains x,
and we will denote it
by the symbol I of x.
Remember, by definition,
all the bundles in this
set can have this property
or will have this property.
That will be that each of them, sorry,
each of them will be indifferent to x.
However, it is important to note
that an indifference set
is not necessarily a curve.
An indifference set could be a band
or a set that is thick, as
we will see in some examples.
Under some assumptions, however,
this indifference set
will indeed become curves,
meaning they will be infinitely thin.
This is an example of
an indifference curve.
Suppose we have bundle 3, 4,
where again x-axis is coffee
and y-axis is orange juice.
So in this, by this statement here,
we're saying that the
bundle 3 ounces of coffee
and 4 cups of orange juice is indifferent
to the bundle of 1 ounce coffee
and 12 cups of orange juice, okay?
So if that is correct,
if that statement is indeed
true for this consumer,
that means that the same
set or, in this case,
the same curve contains both 3, 4
and 1, 12.
In this example, we are also
denoting that the bundle 6, 2
is also in the same indifference set.
There is a notion that is also important
of the weakly preferred set,
which is the area that is preferred
to a whole indifference curve
or some particular bundle.
In this case, the shaded area here
is the weakly preferred set
to this indifference curve denoted by IC,
which is indifference curve
associated with bundles 3, 4,
1, 12, 6, 2, and many other.
Another very interesting question is
whether we have one or
many indifference curves.
In the commodity space, we
typically have infinite.
In fact, we will, in most cases,
have uncountable, infinite
indifference curves.
However, we do not need to draw, you know,
infinite or not even
many indifference curves.
Usually to describe the
consumer preferences
or the corresponding consumer preferences,
we only need to draw
few indifference curves.
The shape of these indifference curves
is in particular the slope
and how curvy they are.
Those are giving or providing information
about these preferences.
In this particular example here,
we have a case in which we have drawn
only four indifference curves,
and we can see that this consumer
has monotonic preferences
because indifference
curves are downward sloped,
and we more or less can
say that this consumer
has similar preferences for Good 1 and 2.
We will see other examples in
which that is not the case.
So other or another set of
concepts that is very important
is that of commodities being good,
bad or neutral, okay?
So a good commodity is the one
that increases the satisfaction
or it is better for the consumer
to have more of it, right?
So that's a good, so for example,
if I'm eating one ounce of chocolate
and eating more chocolate
will make me happier,
I would prefer to eat more chocolate.
Then at that point,
chocolate will be a good commodity for me.
It will increase my satisfaction.
I would prefer to have more of it,
but there are other ones that,
there are other commodities
that could become a bad.
So for example, trash is a
bad in the sense that I want,
I do not want more of it.
I want less of it.
So trash is an example of a bad commodity,
not necessarily something
needs to be bad like all along.
For example, I could regard chocolate good
to a certain point but then
could become a bad to me.
So maybe I can eat all the way
to half a kilogram of chocolate,
and then if I eat more
than that in a week,
let's say a week is the time horizon,
then more of it will actually hurt me.
I will not like to have more
after I have eaten
already half a kilogram.
Maybe I would like to have less.
In that sense, after half a kilogram,
chocolate will become a bad,
and the next concept
is the concept of neutrality.
So a commodity is neutral if I don't care
if I consume more or less of it.
I just don't care.
It doesn't increase nor
decrease my satisfaction
to have more or less of that.
There is a fourth assumption
that is called convexity.
Convexity is the assumption
related to how people,
humans prefer to consume
some form of balance,
balanced bundles, in the sense
that if I have two goods,
in my example, I was using
coffee and orange juice,
in average a consumer
or a typical consumer
would not like to drink only
coffee or only orange juice
but would prefer to have some combination
of these two goods, okay?
So one example would be that
a 50-50 mixture of two bundles,
one bundle having only
coffee and another bundle,
y, having only orange juice,
a 50-50 bundle that combines
the average amount of coffee
between those two bundles, x and y,
and the average amount of orange juice
between those two bundles
could be preferred
to either extreme.
If that is true, then this consumer
obeys this assumption or
follows this assumption
of convexity, okay?
That is, mixture bundles
are weakly preferred
to the extreme bundles.
Let's see how graphically convexity shapes
or gives form to the preferences
and indifference curves.
So again,
we will have two goods,
and we will have, you
know, this will be coffee,
and this will have orange juice,
and we're saying that we have two bundles.
One has only orange juice,
and the other one has only coffee,
and convexity says that
a more balanced bundle,
c, that has kind of an average amount
of coffee between those two bundles,
an average amount of orange
juice between those two bundles
will be preferred to a
or and preferred to c.
So because of that, here
is the important part,
because of that, indifference curves
now can be written or can be
drawn in this way.
Why is that?
Because for this consumer
to prefer z over a and z over b,
the indifference curve
might have this shape.
If they do not have this
shape, this convex shape,
then it wouldn't be true
that c is preferred over a
and c is preferred over b.
Of course, not all
preferences of a on convexity.
The plot that you see and
the figure you're seeing
on your screen right now,
where the darker blue curve
is an indifference curve
and the lighter blue shaded area
is a weakly preferred set,
is such that if the two extreme bundles,
one, or sorry, x and y
are on the same indifference set,
the average one, what in our
previous example was bundle c,
the one here that has the
name of averaged bundle,
that one is not preferred, okay?
So for that bundle not to be preferred,
the indifference curves must look like
this darker blue curve,
and as you can see, the
only way that could happen
is if the preferences are not convex,
do not satisfy convexity.
(gentle music)